<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<?xml-model href="rfc7991bis.rnc"?>  <!-- Required for schema validation and schema-aware editing -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>


<rfc
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  category="std"
  docName="draft-vroonen-idr-bgp-bestpath-nh-selection-00"
  ipr="trust200902"
  obsoletes=""
  updates="4271"
  submissionType="IETF"
  xml:lang="en"
  version="3">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="BGP nh selection enhancements">BGP best path next-hop selection enhancements</title>

    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-vroonen-idr-bgp-bestpath-nh-selection-00"/>

    <author fullname="Olivier Vroonen" initials="O." role="editor" surname="Vroonen">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>
      <address>
        <email>ovroonen@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Stephane Litkowski" initials="S." surname="Litkowski">
      <organization>Cisco</organization>
      <address>
        <email>slitkows@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2025"/>


    <area>Routing</area>
    <workgroup>Interdomain Working Group</workgroup>


    <abstract>
      <t>
      BGP [RFC4271] has originally been designed to carry IPv4 routing information over the Internet. 
      IP routing being “hop-by-hop” in nature, [RFC4271] defines the NEXT_HOP attribute which purpose is to carry the address of the next router to send the IP packet to. 
      In BGP, the next-hop may not be a directly connected router, hence, when evaluating paths, BGP needs to figure out if the next-hop is resolvable and, when needed, needs to figure out what is the internal cost to reach this next-hop. 
      </t>
      <t>
      The incremental use of tunneling technologies to carry traffic between routers (e.g.: GRE, MPLS, SR-MPLS, SRv6…) may violate the assumption that the address carried in the NEXT_HOP attribute is representative of the actual forwarding next-hop.
      These technologies decouple the BGP control-plane's view of the next-hop from the data-plane's actual forwarding endpoint.
      This document describes the problems that arise from this decoupling.
      These problems include sub-optimal path selection, incorrect resolvability tracking of the forwarding path leading to traffic blackholing, and others.
      This document proposes some modification of BGP path selection procedures to accommodate these use cases.
      </t>
    </abstract>
 
  </front>

  <middle>
    
    <section>
        <name>Requirements Language</name>
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
            "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT
            RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be
            interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
            <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in
            all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="introduction">
        <name>Introduction</name>
        <t>
        BGP <xref target="RFC4271"/> is designed to exchange network reachability information between routing domains. 
        A BGP update typically contains a prefix and a set of path attributes, including the well-known mandatory NEXT_HOP attribute. 
        The receiving router uses this next-hop address to determine the egress point for traffic destined for the advertised prefix. 
        The assumption is the next hop address represents the next router from a traffic forwarding point of view.
        </t>
        <t>
        <xref target="RFC4271"/> Section 9.1.2.1 defines the route resolvability condition: a BGP route is considered unresolvable if the BGP speaker’s routing table has no route matching the BGP route next-hop address.
        As per <xref target="RFC4271"/> Section 9.1.2.2 e), when comparing paths received via internal BGP (IBGP), the Routing Table metric associated to the BGP route next-hop address is used to figure out the best path.
        </t>
        <figure>
        <artwork><![CDATA[
                +------+ 
                | RTR1 |----------------+
                +------+       (1)      |
                                        |
                                    +------+
                                    | RTR3 |
                                    +------+
                                        |
                +------+       (2)      |
                | RTR2 |----------------+
                +------+ 
          ]]>
        </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
        RTR3 receives prefix P/m from RTR1 and RTR2 with NEXT_HOP N1 and N2. N1 resolution have a cost of 1, N2 resolution have a cost of 2.
        Based on <xref target="RFC4271"/> procedures, RTR3 will select the path with the lowest cost to the NEXT_HOP address, so RTR3 will select the path received from RTR1.
        </t>
        <t>
        This document describes cases where the NEXT_HOP attribute used in the BGP update is not representative of the actual forwarding path. 
        In these cases, the resolvability condition may fail in its goal and path selection may be done on inaccurate criteria leading to suboptimal routing, network congestion, traffic blackholing...
        </t>
        <t>
        These use cases are not new and may have been partially addressed by IETF standards or drafts, some references are provided below:
        </t>
        <ul>
            <li>
            <xref target="I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-bestpath-selection-criteria"/> addresses the case of MPLS networks and proposes a modification of the route resolvability condition to be performed using forwarding database of a particular data plane protocol. 
            It also proposes an optional data path verification.
            </li>
            <li>
            <xref target="RFC9012"/> Section 7 improves the route resolvability condition by verifying that there is a feasible tunnel. However, it doesn’t take into account that the cost associated with the tunnel may be different from the cost associated with the BGP next-hop.
            </li>
            <li>
            <xref target="RFC9252"/> defines SRv6 overlay services signaling using BGP. The procedures involve the advertisement of an SRv6 Service TLV within the BGP Prefix SID attribute to signal the SID to be used for forwarding. RFC9252 highlights that ingress PE must perform a resolvability check for the SRv6 SID in addition to the resolvability check done on the NEXT_HOP attribute. However, it doesn’t take into account that the cost associated with the tunnel may be different from the cost associated with the BGP next-hop.
            </li>
        </ul>
        <t>
        This document defines generic modifications to the BGP decision process that can apply to all the use cases.
        </t>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Use cases">
      <section title="Tunnel encapsulation attribute">
      </section>
      <section title="Segment Routing Traffic Engineering policy">
        <t>
        When using SRTE policies <xref target="RFC9256"/> , the BGP NEXT_HOP attribute may not accurately represent the actual forwarding path.
        </t>
        <figure>
          <name>SRTE policies example</name>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                +-----+ (1) +----+  (1)
                | PE1 |-----| P1 |-----+
                +-----+ [5] +----+  [5]|
                       \   /           |
                    (5) \ / (1)     +-----+
                         X          | PE3 |
                    [1] / \ [5]     +-----+
                       /   \           |
                +-----+ [2] +----+  [1]|
                | PE2 |-----| P2 |-----+
                +-----+ (6) +----+  (5)
          ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
        In the above figure, a BGP VPN is deployed over PEs. Let's assume PE3 receives prefix P/m from PE1 and PE2 with NEXT_HOP N1, N2 and color C1.
        On PE3, policies with color C1 towards N1 and N2 are configured to use the low latency path (P2 path).
        </t>
        <ul>
            <li>Costs in parentheses represents cost of IGP.</li>
            <li>Costs in brackets represents cost of te-metric (Traffic Engineering Metric)</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section title="SRv6 services">
        <t>
        When using SRv6 services as defined in <xref target="RFC9252"/>, the BGP NEXT_HOP attribute may not be representative of the actual forwarding path.
        </t>
        <figure>
          <name>SRv6 service example</name>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
                +-----+ (1) +----+  (1)
                | PE1 |-----| P1 |-----+
                +-----+ [5] +----+  [5]|
                       \   /           |
                    (5) \ / (1)     +-----+
                         X          | PE3 |
                    [1] / \ [5]     +-----+
                       /   \           |
                +-----+ [2] +----+  [1]|
                | PE2 |-----| P2 |-----+
                +-----+ (6) +----+  (5)
          ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
        In the above figure, an SRv6-based BGP VPN is deployed over PEs. Let's assume PE3 receives prefix P/m from PE1 and PE2 with NEXT_HOP N1, N2 and SRv6 SID S1 and S2.
        SID S1 and S2 are allocated from flex-algo 129 (low latency) locators.
        </t>
        <ul>
            <li>Costs in parentheses represents cost of algo 0 (as defined in <xref target="RFC8665"/> Section 8.5).</li>
            <li>Costs in brackets represents cost of flex algo <xref target="RFC9350"/> 129 (low latency).</li>
        </ul>
        <t>
        The routing table of PE3 contains the following entries:
        </t>
        <ul>
            <li>N1 is resolved via P1 path (Shortest Path First (SPF) path) and S1 via P2 path (low latency path).</li>
            <li>N2 is resolved via P1 path (SPF path) and S2 via P2 path (low latency path).</li>
        </ul>
        <t>
        Based on <xref target="RFC4271"/> procedures, PE3 will select the path with the lowest cost to the NEXT_HOP address.
        Cost to N1 is lower than cost to N2, so PE3 will select the path received from PE1.
        However, the forwarding path to reach P/m when using the path received from PE1 is PE3->P2->PE1.
        </t>
        <t>
        Two problems may arise:
        </t>
        <ul>
            <li>PE3 will not try to resolve S1, which may lead to traffic blackholing if the path to S1 is not reachable.</li>
            <li>PE3 do not select the best path based on the lowest latency intent to reach P/m as it will only consider the cost to the NEXT_HOP address.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section title="MPLS path">
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section title="Modification of the BGP route selection process">
        <section title="Forwarding address">
            <t>
            This document defines the forwarding address as the IP address of the next hop that will be used to forward packets. The forwarding address may come from the NEXT_HOP or a different address which has been signaled in a different attribute along with the path.
            </t>
            <t>
            The following data already defined in BGP standards SHOULD be considered as forwarding addresses:
            </t>
            <ul>
                <li>The Tunnel Egress Endpoint Sub-TLV contained in Tunnel Encapsulation attribute defined in <xref target="RFC9012"/></li>
                <li>SRv6 SID Information Sub-TLV contained within L3 or L2 SRv6 SID defined in <xref target="RFC9252"/></li>
            </ul>
            <t>
            Unless a BGP update contains another type of forwarding address, the BGP NEXT_HOP attribute is considered as the forwarding address.
            </t>
            <t>
            A forwarding address MAY be accompanied by additional data (we call it forwarding context) that characterizes more the forwarding path to be used. As an example, <xref target="RFC9012"/> defines encapsulation sub-TLVs: the information contained in these TLVs can be used as additional context to the forwarding address. 
            When <xref target="RFC9252"/> is used, it is easy to assume that the forwarding context is SRv6 forwarding.
            </t>
            <t>
            Each new BGP extension SHOULD specify if an address carried by the extension must be considered as a forwarding address. The procedures defined in the next section SHOULD apply for any new forwarding address defined without having to redefine them.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="lookup-in-table" title="Lookup table">
        <t>
        When the forwarding address and its context are identified for a BGP route, the implementation must figure out the internal table in which to perform the address look up. 
        Each implementation has its own set of tables (e.g.: IP routing table, Ingress MPLS tunnel table, …), so each implementation figures out the proper internal table to use based on the forwarding address and the context.
        </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Route resolvability condition">
        <t>
            This document updates <xref target="RFC4271"/> Section 9.1.2.1 as follows:
        </t>
        <ul>
            <li>
                The route resolvability check for the BGP NEXT_HOP attribute MUST continue to be done.
            </li>
            <li>
                In addition, the route resolvability criteria SHOULD be performed based on the forwarding address.
            </li>
            <li>
                When resolving the forwarding address, look up SHOULD be performed in the table identified from the forwarding address and context.
            </li>
        </ul>
        </section>
        <section title="Internal cost determination">
        <t>
        For a prefix P/m, different BGP paths may use different forwarding addresses and contexts of various types.
        </t>
        <figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
        P/m
            Path1: NH=R1 Color: 200
            Path2: NH=R2 SRv6-SID: R2_SID
            Path3: NH=R3 Tunnel-encap(L2TPv3, endpoint: R3)
            ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>
        Costs retrieved from different types of forwarding addresses or contexts may not be comparable because they are based on different sets of rules. For instance, path1 may leverage an SR-TE policy (color 200, endpoint R1) optimizing for latency, so the cost of path1 will reflect the latency to R1. Path2 may use the IGP cost to R2. Path3 may have no cost. These values are not directly comparable.
        </t>
        <t>
        In order to compare the paths, this document introduces the concept of forwarding address preference. The preference value may come from the table lookup, or BGP local configuration may override it (for example, SR policies with color 200 may have the highest preference, while L2TP tunnels may have the lowest preference).
        </t>
        <t>
        This document updates <xref target="RFC4271"/> Section 9.1.2.2 e) as follows:
        </t>
        <ul>
            <li>
            Remove from consideration any routes with less forwarding address preference. The forwarding preference of a path is determined by either retrieval from the appropriate table identified in <xref target="lookup-in-table"/> or by local BGP configuration.
            </li>
            <li>
            For remaining paths, the interior cost of a route is determined by retrieving the metric to the forwarding address for the route from the appropriate table identified in <xref target="lookup-in-table"/>. If the forwarding address for a route is reachable, but no cost can be determined, the cost SHOULD be set by default to the maximum allowed cost.
            </li>
        </ul>
        <t>
        Using forwarding preference and forwarding address-based cost SHOULD be enabled through a configuration knob.
        </t>

        </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Examples">
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>This document does not require any IANA actions.</t>
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="Security">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
      This document modifies BGP route selection process by using data other than the next-hop address to perform the resolvability check as well as to compute the internal cost. 
      This does not add any security consideration compared to using the existing NEXT_HOP attribute defined in <xref target="RFC4271"/>.
      </t>
    </section>
    
    
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4271.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8665.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9012.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9252.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9256.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.9350.xml"/>
      </references>
 
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-idr-bgp-bestpath-selection-criteria.xml"/>

      </references>
    </references>
    

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" numbered="false">
      <name>Acknowledgements</name>
      <t></t>
    </section>
    
    
 </back>
</rfc>